So let's dive into this.
Hardware engineering part and let's
continue with this Velma DNS stations
last notes and naming principles.
That is our topic for today.
Last time we were checking the roles of
these different servers in development
DNA.
We were checking the process based on the
PCs, roles and features,
a little bit about the hardware options
there.
Then we check the role of the backup
station and hardware here there as well.
Same thing for alarm station slash alarm
server.
And the engineering activity server and
there we stopped that last time.
And we were discussing that in
development DNA,
the system is very flexible,
so we can combine different stations
together like the ARM station and backup
station.
Those can be combined in the same
hardware or distributed in the different
hardware.
Depending on the solution,
is it a big or small system?
Is it the industrial or this kind of like
a learning environment?
We can create a different kind of like
combination of stations,
what kind of functions they are handling.
Today we are going a little bit deeper
how we can combine different features
into the one one like a station or
hardware and how it is done in
development DMA and what is like the
background.
Why we are doing this way?
I'm simultaneously opening the other
material of the element DNA.
This is the general section.
We are referring that one as well.
So here are some background information
from that.
That's how it was done in the Volumet DNA
system.
This slot feature we are referring it.
So here's a picture of that Volumet DNA
XD era or Damatic XD.
Like it was introduced here back into 88,
one was introduced this automatic XD
automation system and back in the days in
the 80s.
Those different features are combined in
the one station.
These kind of physical slots,
if you remember from the last time when
we were there at the lab,
you saw those IO cards in the top of the
cabinet.
There are those kind of brass kind of IO
cards there in the upper part of the
cabinet. Those were the IO cards.
In that era,
also the stations were that kind of cars,
but just in a bigger format.
Those are like a 1U size of the cars.
Those are about this height of cars,
but the station cars were bigger, like 3U.
Three times longer cars and those were
stacked just like the IO cards are there
in the laboratory.
So back in the day,
store physical cars in rack and we could
combine different features to one station.
For example,
like a process lesson like this,
we could add their CPUs, NCUs,
which are like a network control units,
NCU, just like here. Here is 1 NCU unit.
Like a car there installed in the rack,
there is CPU and CU and there is no label
in the middle one,
but that is the FBC feed boost controller
that Miller bot over there.
And there could be backup station.
Different kind of feature can be there
installed in the rack and combine
different features in one station.
But the FPC is referred here in the
process station part. This is that.
Field bus pass controller which handles
for example the IO cards.
Back in the days it was only the
centralized IO,
the rack IO which is available there in
the lab in the upper part of the.
IO cabinet.
It could be also Profibus or something
like that it was handling.
But also because this system need to be
backward compatible,
this kind of feature needs to be
implemented also in this violent DNA era.
It was introduced in 2000 or something
like that when we were starting to use
those industrial pieces like.
AC and RT or something like this.
So maybe we have that kind of feature
there as well without those physical
slots.
So that's one of those things that the
systems need to be backward compatible,
so that those old style dramatic XD era
process stations could be implemented
with this newer.
Industrial PC type of controllers with
the Linux Linux system and so on.
That's why we need,
we need to have another solution and the
solution we are virtualizing those slots
in operating system level.
That's why we are still having that slot
thing.
It is well met DNA which was physical
team in a a dramatic XD era,
but nowadays it is like virtual
virtualized slots.
In a Valment DNA and we are using this
slot controller or X slot to handle that
function in a Valment DNA.
Let's check first this process station
which is running the Linux system.
There is this kind of program there.
Inside that Linux which handled the
virtualized slots which were physical
thing in the dynamic XD era.
But now those are here virtualized.
We can see in the third block the first.
Column tells the slot number.
There is a PCS which means the post
process controller functionality and the
name of that one is GP01.
That is like a CPU part.
The PCs of the process station,
just like it was in a rack version,
the automatic XD,
there is a CPU slot reserved for our
process station,
but as we can see for example the NCU.
The network controller unit,
we are having the same thing running here
in the slot 16,
which is handling the communication from
that process station to other stations in
a network.
So the NCU handles that kind of
functionality.
It is preserving slot #16 as we can see.
What about the other things here?
We can see a couple of FBCS which are the
field bus controllers in our solution.
This is this screenshot is from that.
Process station in the DP66 lab,
the GP 01.
There's a couple of FPC's running inside
of the Linux and there's GP 01M2M5.
M6 and then there is M9.
Those are the important things you need
to understand.
If we refer this slot feature,
we are checking the same thing from that
system layout.
We can see that there is this AC and Mr.
which is running the Linux.
And inside of there there is a software
slots reserved for the feed bus
controllers.
As we can see in the picture,
the AC and I/O is reserving one of those
FB CS and the slot number for this one is
always the FBC two,
which means it is running in the slot #2.
That is reserved for this AC and IO,
those black IO cards nearby to Mr.
controller.
There is also configured M5 and M6.
And if we are checking those from the
layout,
the M5 and M6 can be found here in the
system layout and those are for the
Profibus devices.
So there's this virtualized slots M5 and
M6 and we can use that slot to
communicate with the Profibus devices and
there is also reservation for M4,
but that is not configured there.
The slot #4 that is M.
So that is like like a reserve.
Tropy bus network available there,
but that is not configured there,
that's empty there.
So we could take that into use.
If we are adding some process or devices
to our lab, we could implement that there.
And it's very easy to add new features to
the CPU.
We can just configure their additional
slots to handle that,
for example new new like a field bus
controllers for example.
This IBC is related to also the list.
Let's don't,
let's don't focus on that one because
that information is not needed in this
course.
So let's leave that little bit like we
don't need it.
And there's also this kind of things like
DP Mon,
which is Profibus DP monitoring software
and same thing for Profinet monitoring.
That is for the diagnostic purposes of
the field buses.
You will see that those are really nice.
If we compare for example Siemens system,
we don't have that kind of like a loop to
the field devices.
What kind of devices are is connected to
our station with those DPMON and PMMON
softwares,
we can have a nice visual overview of.
Different like devices which are
connected to our station.
We will check it later on,
but these kind of features are quite nice
here in the Velma DNA.
So I want you to like look around this
picture and compare this configuration of
slots and same thing here in this process
station.
System layout view and think about the
look around different features which have
been implemented there.
But this example was the process test and
running Linux system.
But the same thing applies also to those
Windows servers as well.
We are having the slot controller for one
station and as we can see there are still
the slot numbers here.
From slot one to slot 16 and the same
view from the system layout for the same
station.
We can see that this one PC which is the
name of that one is G109.
We will come later on this naming policy,
but this is like the operating station
which also covers the functionality of
backup.
GB01 and also the alarm station G1A1.
And that is done with exactly the same
principle.
We are having that of virtualized slots
and the first slot number one is running
GB 01. This is the backup station code.
As you can see it is Windows executable.
Just the one executable there which is
running the backup station functionality.
And the slot #3 is handling CDMGR,
which is the same as the operate,
which is the user interface in a valve
DNA. G 109 is actually to operate the HMI.
Slash the operator interface over here
and the G1A1 is the alarm station.
It is running the alarm station
executable there and so that way.
We can combine different features,
features to one station.
We are calling this node or slots here in
development DNA slot is coming from here
and the node name is over here.
That's how we can combine different
features to one station.
How we are doing that? We are not.
We are not using this.
System configurator.
In our like like how do I call it in our
exercises in this course,
but just how it is done in the
environment DNA.
Here we can see for example this open
dialogue.
This is from GB01 and it is ACNMR
generation 2 hardware.
We are first tracking here correct
hardware we are using and then we are
just tracking and dropping here different
feature,
different features for that process.
And we are adding here the IP addresses,
the name and so on and we can build the
structure over here and this is the way
that hardware is gone bigger and
maintained if we need to do something
like a addition there.
We are tracking and dropping feature and
then downloading the software to that
process station. Actually,
as we were talking earlier,
we are downloading the configuration to
the backup station.
This is the part if we are doing that
kind of configuration changes in that
hardware,
you are downloading the software first to
the backup station and it is hosting all
the configuration for different stations.
Here we first download and then the into
the backup station and then we if we
reboot that process station,
those configurations are taking into use
when that process station is starting up.
That's the way download procedure
functions here in development DNA.
Also for this kind of system
configurating things.
Also back in the days this system
configurator is quite new to environment
DNA.
This is actually just a user interface to
text based files.
This is creating text based files.
This user interface.
Back in the days when I was starting the
Vomit DNA configuration,
all those things need to be done manually
in a text files.
Row by row it was very time consuming and
we couldn't have this kind of nice
overview of our system.
All those configurations were just text
files, fails, text fails,
text files in those.
In that backup space and all the
configuration was there,
but now we are having this kind of system
configurator.
We are checking the futures features of
this one,
but you don't need to use this tool in
our course courses,
but just for the information.
How it is done?
That was basically the slot thing.
Any questions of this slot feature here
in Valor PMA?
In the next exercise we are using the
slot names,
so you need to know what does it mean.
But everything is once again happening
under the bonnet.
You need to just know the principles in
the environment DNA,
but everything's happened happening under
the bonnet when we are creating the
software.
This is just kind of nice to know
information to you.
OK, if there's no any questions,
let's continue with the naming,
naming principle and Valent DNA.
And how those are used here to categorize
different parts and so on so.
We need to have this kind of naming
principle which applies to all Valmet
systems and we are having here some
examples to you.
We have been talking about the process
station GB01 backup station GB.
011 for example,
let's let's go a little bit deeper into
that naming policy.
As we were talking last time,
development DNA system is done with the
subsystems.
So if we can like divide a big system to
smaller parts with the subsystem feature,
for example here in our campus we are
having the Z system and E system.
So the G subsystem is for automation lab
things in the next room and the E system
is for the energy technology in the lab
DP39. That way we can divide.
Those two systems.
We are having two different processes.
One is this basically this water process
over here which is using this G subsystem
and E subsystem is reserved for those
energy technology devices.
In a lab DP39.
That's why we are having two different
subsystems.
We are dividing two different processes.
Here in campus that also helps like a
maintain of the system in a like if if
you're using a power plant plant for
example like some of the processes like
the boiler can be in the one subsystem.
And some features like um.
For example, they.
Material handling. They're all like that.
If we are, for example,
burning coal or that like conveyors and
so on can be in a different subsystem,
we can do a maintenance for the energy
feed for the coal.
Cold feeding system without disturbing
the main boiler and we cannot shut it
down just like that, but like the feeding,
we can shut shut it down for a
momentarily if we need to do some
maintenance there to that sub system.
That's why those are divided into
different subsystems.
And from there we can have a different
control rules for one subsystem.
For example, those are labeled like G1.
G2 E 1E2 as we can see for example here.
Our alarm station and the operate station,
those are G1 something.
That means they are using the G1 control
room in our subsystem.
G means that is a G.
Subsystem and E means that is part of the
energy technology system.
Actually we are having here just one
control room per subsystem.
So we are actually in our system having
only G1 and E1 control room available.
That is one of those naming principles
and there's also this station type code
if we are looking for example this GP01
which we were looking earlier there in
the laboratory.
It means that G is the subsystem and the
P means it is a process controller.
There's different features we are
labeling here.
Key means it is a process controller and
for the alarm station it is AB means
backup station,
E is engineering activity server.
O means operator station and D is a
diagnostic station for example.
As we can see,
for example here our backup station,
there is a backup station GP01G10.
It is a G1 operating room.
O means it's operating station and there
is a 9 which is like a rolling rolling
number.
We can add a couple of different
operating station and so on.
G1A1 mean it means that it is a.
Control rule G1 part of the G subsystem A.
In this case it means it's alarm station
and it is the first alarm station in that
control rule.
That's how we are naming our different
stations and development DNA and we
already know from the name,
for example GP01 that it is part of the G
system.
So it is controlling those devices in
this next laboratory.
It it would be like EP01 like.
Probably here.
If we are locking those stations in that.
Energy Technology Lab there's EP01EP02.
That means that there's two process
stations and those are part of the E
subsystem Energy Technology P means
process station and 01/02.
It divides those two stations from each
other.
And the same thing applies to all Volumet
system if you go to for example the power
plant there in.
All of up, for example,
there is a subsystem for.
For different like power plants,
for example the Keliolati power plant is
having is it the E system and Bravahalati
power plant is having A system and so on.
I don't remember those.
For subsystem names from at the moment,
but that is like the principle in a
actual meals and power plants and so on.
Here's a couple of examples how that
naming principle works.
GP 01 is subsystem G backup station and
it's number one and same thing for
subsystem E.
EB01 is the backup station for E
subsystem.
That's like the principle here.
And the things you need to cover in this
course is this power process, controller,
alarm station,
backup station and operator station.
That is basically the things you need in
this course.
So you need to divide those by its name.
When I'm talking for example GB 01,
you need to understand that it is the IT
is the subsystem G process controller.
That is the main thing.
OK.
Yeah.
Any questions about this name in policy?
Yep.
Yeah.
Do we have any examples here?
Over.
Down Profibus. OK,
this is this is named for just that if
you are looking at the system layout here
in the GB01-PB.
This is just a label for this Profibus
control. This is Profibus transformer.
I don't know how to call this device,
but this is the device under the process
that is physically there.
We are having the network connector here
and that is changing the RJ 45 connection
to this Profibus the.
9 connectors,
so that is just name for this prophy bus.
Converter.
If we check out a label from this device,
there should be a label there.
It is a GP01 which means the process
station and there the Bravi bus.
Uh, profit boost.
Yeah, that is like a hub.
Basically we can connect with that device
3 Profibus networks to one station.
Excuse me, SW. Yeah, that is a switch.
That also means that GB 01 means the
process station and this is actually the
FBC number,
the slot where the FBC for this profinet
is configured and there's a switch.
Then there's only one switch.
I don't know what is the label SV10,
it's probably better naming policy would
be S SW01,
but that is how it is done in this system.
Yeah, IP address here and there.
Are they like fixed? For example,
the IP address is on the.
Is it like something fixed or we can just
enter anything you want?
There is a policy for the IP addresses.
How those are used in the different
subsystems?
Basically there's one like AC class
network reserved for one subsystem.
If we are looking for example here in the
system layout, we can see that.
Actually it is not applying here,
but usually.
Isn't that a good example?
Because our GP and EP process bases,
those are the in the different subsystem,
but usually those are also in a different
sub networks.
That is like the way it is done in the
industry.
But those are also in a different IP
address area,
so it is easier easier also in the
network configuration to divide
communication between the subsystems when
those are in the different networks as
well.
Any other questions?
If not,
let's do one thing before we are having a
break, that is.
Here in our our schedule for today and
The thing is we are getting the remote
access to Valmet DNA and there is.
One document here in this next section in
the IO application engineering and
there's this vomit DNA remote access.
So we are looking at this document over
here and for the beginning before you do
anything this is basically.
If you are using development DNA for
example from your home,
then you are using this remote dot yonk
dot FI address and you can access
development DNA where wherever you are
just with that remote connection.
And you can get the access to the EIS
wherever.
If you are using that,
you are following these steps over here,
but in this classroom we are actually
taking a direct like the remote desktop
from.
From here and you are doing it this way.
You are typing here.
Remote desktop connection.
Oh.
Or look it up from the start menu,
just open the remote desktop connection
and from there you are having this kind
of dialogue.
You are typing here EAS-G.
That means we are taking a remote
connection to our engineering activity
server in a GE subsystem.
When you press connect,
if it is giving a dialogue that you can
enter the like the passcode, skip it.
You need to have this kind of dialogue.
You can enter your username which is your
e-mail address.
And from there just use the regular
password you are using in our systems.
This is in the AD.
It can connect you into that PC.
Just type.
Your password there and it is asking this
dialogue.
Just click yes and you should have your.
EASG remote connection opening there.
And in the end you should have there some
kind of window.
Desktop open there and if you get this
open this is correct.
It is probably taking some time now in
the first time because everyone is
opening at the same time and you are
logging in here logging in here.
First time it is building those in your
user like configuration to the server and
that's kind of things. That's why.
Let's open this in this point and let's
have a break now.
So that we can give the server some time
to recover from that huge load because
everyone is logging there the first time.
Did you get this open? This kind of view?
Nice. Let's have a break then.